<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tavish Armstrong</title>
    <link>http://tavisharmstrong.com/tags/tv/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tavish Armstrong</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://tavisharmstrong.com/tags/tv/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Shows I&#39;ve been watching</title>
      <link>http://tavisharmstrong.com/2015/07/12/shows-ive-been-watching</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 22:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tavisharmstrong.com/2015/07/12/shows-ive-been-watching</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I learned to knit. Part of the appeal for me is that it&amp;rsquo;s very easy to sit down, knit some stitches, and make progress. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to screw up so badly you have to start over, but for the most part it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to take large steps backward. Unlike with programming, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to knit a scarf so badly it causes active harm to you and the people around you. If you&amp;rsquo;re patient, you&amp;rsquo;ll eventually have a scarf or a sweater, and no matter how many stiches you accidentally added in the wrong places, you still have something that represents a tonne of work to be proud of. Also you are now warmer than you were before, which is kind of cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One nice thing about knitting is that you can do it while you watch television. Some shows I&amp;rsquo;ve been watching lately:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The West Wing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adventure Time&lt;/em&gt;, which is hilarious and cuter than a show has any right to be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bomb Girls&lt;/em&gt;, which follows the stories of the workers of a Toronto munitions factory during WWII. Like &lt;em&gt;The Bletchley Circle&lt;/em&gt;, it focuses on parts of the war effort that are not usually explored in war movies, viz., the home front. It also spends some time on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian-Canadian_internment&#34;&gt;darker parts of Canadian history&lt;/a&gt;, which I appreciate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sense8&lt;/em&gt;, the new Netflix show from The Wachowskis and J. Michael Straczynski. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aphyr/status/617943823243546625&#34;&gt;This show is great&lt;/a&gt;. And hey, some of it takes place in SF which is kind of neat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This fluff post is brought to you by a few weeks of travel and strep throat. Pro-tip: don&amp;rsquo;t get strep throat.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>