<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tavish Armstrong</title>
    <link>http://example.org/tags/architecture/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tavish Armstrong</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://example.org/tags/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog your mistakes, please</title>
      <link>http://example.org/2013/11/13/blog-your-mistakes-please</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2013 00:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/2013/11/13/blog-your-mistakes-please</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week I read a neat post by Sarah Mei called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sarahmei.com/blog/2013/11/11/why-you-should-never-use-mongodb/&#34;&gt;Why You Should Never
Use MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;. Usually I would skip a blog post with that title, but
for some reason I stuck with it, and I&amp;rsquo;m glad I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually don&amp;rsquo;t like titles like &amp;ldquo;why you should never use MongoDB&amp;rdquo; because the
author usually means &amp;ldquo;why you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t use MongoDB if you are me and you are
using it in the specific way I am using it and you are in the specific business
that I work for.&amp;rdquo; The author writes the snappy title because it looks good on
the Hacker News front page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t that kind of blog post, though, and she makes a compelling argument
that almost earns the title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be &amp;ldquo;Why &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; Should Never Use MongoDB&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;m being pedantic,
but I think the emphasis makes the point clearer. The post is making an
assumption about you, and that assumption is this: you are not as smart as she
is and if you are not as smart as she is, how can you hope to avoid the problem
she is describing? I am not as smart as she is, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to learn from her
mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m an inexperienced software developer; a n00b. I haven&amp;rsquo;t watched a large
software system go from infancy to smouldering ruins, nor have I watched design
decisions explode in my face nine months after making them. And how could I
have? I&amp;rsquo;m an undergraduate student and there aren&amp;rsquo;t enough months of summer
jobs to string together to create those experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have many of these experiences of my own, I&amp;rsquo;m forced to use the
experiences of others. Let&amp;rsquo;s call these &lt;a href=&#34;http://aosabook.org/en/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;prosthetic experiences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Brave, humble, smart folks like Sarah Mei, who can talk about the projects
they&amp;rsquo;ve seen crash and burn, are a boon; prosthetic experiences can help me
think about design tradeoffs in ways I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise be able to without
dealing with those problems myself.  They help me develop paranoia in the right
places. Hopefully, it&amp;rsquo;ll help me avoid boring mistakes and make more
interesting messes instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not fun to write about your mistakes. But I like it when you do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>