<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tavish Armstrong</title>
    <link>http://tavisharmstrong.com/tags/coding/feeds/atom.all/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tavish Armstrong</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://tavisharmstrong.com/tags/coding/feeds/atom.all/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>NBDiff: A diffing and merging tool for the IPython Notebook</title>
      <link>http://tavisharmstrong.com/2014/04/06/nbdiff-a-diffing-and-merging-tool-for-the-ipython-notebook</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2014 15:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tavisharmstrong.com/2014/04/06/nbdiff-a-diffing-and-merging-tool-for-the-ipython-notebook</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Final-year engineering students at many universities have to complete a &amp;ldquo;Capstone&amp;rdquo; project that gives them a chance to apply everything they learned throughout school to a practical, hands-on group project. My team just finished ours &amp;ndash; a project called &lt;a href=&#34;http://nbdiff.org&#34;&gt;NBDiff&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; and I&amp;rsquo;m happy to report that it was a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve spoken to me in the last couple years, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard me ramble about the IPython Notebook, a rich web-based environment for scientific computing. Well, that project is wonderful, but there&amp;rsquo;s a catch with working on notebook files: the file format is a giant JSON blob and makes version control tricky. If you use &lt;code&gt;git diff&lt;/code&gt;, it can be hard to understand what you&amp;rsquo;ve actually changed, and if you need to resolve a merge conflict? Fasten your seatbelt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NBDiff takes a stab at making these tasks easier. It presents diffs in a two-pane format and shows you deleted/added cells how you originally saw them in the notebook: if an image was changed, you see the image instead of a 10000-line diff of a base64 encoded PNG file. When resolving merge conflicts, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about mangling the JSON by hand &amp;ndash; you just drag and drop changes into the final version and click &amp;lsquo;save&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/nbdiff-screenshots/main-screenshot.png&#34; alt=&#34;A screenshot of nbdiff&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as school projects go, this one was very satisfying. We have 50 GitHub stars and several hundred downloads already; I can actually use it to solve problems &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;; and the IPython folks are interested in seeing it maintained beyond Capstone. Considering many school projects &amp;ndash; even Capstone projects &amp;ndash; never see the light of day, let alone continued maintenance, I&amp;rsquo;m really happy about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homepage: &lt;a href=&#34;http://nbdiff.org&#34;&gt;nbdiff.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub repo: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tarmstrong/nbdiff&#34;&gt;tarmstrong/nbdiff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyPI package: &lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/nbdiff&#34;&gt;nbdiff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/nbdiff-screenshots/stars.png&#34; alt=&#34;50 github stars and counting&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Git Harness</title>
      <link>http://tavisharmstrong.com/2013/11/24/the-git-harness</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2013 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tavisharmstrong.com/2013/11/24/the-git-harness</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Git&amp;rsquo;s usefulness far surpasses the frustration caused by its clunky interface, so I don&amp;rsquo;t like to bash it. It was the first version control system I learned, and I learned it before I could program much more than CS101 assignments. Throughout the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve used various languages and various version control systems, but Git is the only one I&amp;rsquo;ve used seriously for any amount of time. So not only do I not like to bash it — I lack the perspective necessary for critique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, most people can agree on one thing: the interface sucks. Git is a powerful tool, but it&amp;rsquo;s almost impossible to learn how all the commands and their options work. The arguments have inconsistent orders, and the flags mean different things in different contexts. Some of the commands share duties with others. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to deal with it — it involves reading the man pages every time you want to use &lt;code&gt;git branch&lt;/code&gt; — but it is a struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complaining is fun, but it isn&amp;rsquo;t going to get us anywhere —  how do we go about fixing this problem instead? Is the answer a slick GUI like the GitHub desktop client? For some people, sure. But too many GUIs solve the wrong problem: &lt;em&gt;affordance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Affordance is the idea that you should be able to figure out how to use parts of an interface intuitively. Buttons should look like they can be pressed, editable text should look like it can be edited, etc. Command line tools generally solve this problem with man pages and usage messages — and that&amp;rsquo;s a powerful mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t let you predict the outcome of your actions. Git forces you to have a solid mental model of how a Git history works. You have to understand what the various commands do to that mental model, and be able to simulate a proposed action in your head. Most of us developed this mental model through using Git and making a lot of mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice makes perfect, but there is no virtue in unnecessary struggle. We &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; build a Git interface that helps novices develop their mental models faster, with less pain. We could do it without hiding the complexities of Git, too. And I think we should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This&lt;/em&gt; is the Git interface that I would actually want to use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-napkin-sketch&#34;&gt;The Napkin Sketch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people who know how to use Git have a conceptual model of a Git log that looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/git-diagrams/basic-vis.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you&amp;rsquo;ve got the initial state of the repository &amp;ndash; the files that were there when you started. Then you have a set of commits (or &amp;ldquo;changes&amp;rdquo;) that transform those initial files into what they are today in the &lt;code&gt;HEAD&lt;/code&gt; version. The state of the working directory is indicated by the &lt;code&gt;HEAD&lt;/code&gt; ref. In the above diagram, our &lt;code&gt;HEAD&lt;/code&gt; is pointed at &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use Git, you probably understand this. You might visualize it differently — maybe your arrows go the other way, or maybe you like a vertical graph. In any case, this visualization helps you make decisions about what to do next, depending on your goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have some unstaged changes in your working directory. You start typing &lt;code&gt;git commit -a&lt;/code&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/git-diagrams/adding-a-commit-start-typing.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and when the interface realizes what command you&amp;rsquo;re typing in, it shows you a preview of what will happen if you hit enter. First, it creates a new commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/git-diagrams/adding-a-commit-pre-refmove.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then it updates &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;HEAD&lt;/code&gt; to point to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/git-diagrams/adding-a-commit.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you haven&amp;rsquo;t hit enter yet. This lets you understand the change you&amp;rsquo;re about to make. If it&amp;rsquo;s not what you wanted, you have a chance to avoid running that command and having to correct your mistake — which is especially difficult for novices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another situation. You have a &lt;code&gt;dev&lt;/code&gt; branch and you want to take a look at the files in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/git-diagrams/basic-branch-vis.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You try &lt;code&gt;git checkout dev&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/git-diagrams/checking-out-a-branch-typing.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It fades the current &lt;code&gt;HEAD&lt;/code&gt; and shows you where your new &lt;code&gt;HEAD&lt;/code&gt; will be after hitting enter. If that&amp;rsquo;s what you want, you can run that command and feel confident you&amp;rsquo;re doing the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to check it out, though. Instead, you want to merge &lt;code&gt;dev&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;. This is what the preview shows you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://tavisharmstrong.com/git-diagrams/git-merge.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interpreting this is a challenge, and probably gives little solace to a bewildered novice. Once you get over the conceptual hurdles behind Git, though, you can start to experiment a bit, without fear of breaking your repository. It means you can try out a command and figure out for yourself whether it&amp;rsquo;s going to do what you want without having to ask your friend the Git wizard if it&amp;rsquo;s going to break stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea reminds me of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jumpharness.com/skate%20harness%20system.jpg&#34;&gt;figure skating harnesses&lt;/a&gt;. When you&amp;rsquo;re learning to do a double salchow, your coach will often strap you into one of those. You are then free to throw yourself into the jump without fear of falling on your ass. You get to try things out without suffering the consequences, so that you can develop good habits before it hurts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Git, the idea is the same, but instead of falling on your ass,
you&amp;rsquo;re avoiding an hour of sifting through your reflogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So: who wants to build the Git harness?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog your mistakes, please</title>
      <link>http://tavisharmstrong.com/2013/11/13/blog-your-mistakes-please</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2013 00:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tavisharmstrong.com/2013/11/13/blog-your-mistakes-please</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week I read a neat post by Sarah Mei called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sarahmei.com/blog/2013/11/11/why-you-should-never-use-mongodb/&#34;&gt;Why You Should Never
Use MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;. Usually I would skip a blog post with that title, but
for some reason I stuck with it, and I&amp;rsquo;m glad I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually don&amp;rsquo;t like titles like &amp;ldquo;why you should never use MongoDB&amp;rdquo; because the
author usually means &amp;ldquo;why you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t use MongoDB if you are me and you are
using it in the specific way I am using it and you are in the specific business
that I work for.&amp;rdquo; The author writes the snappy title because it looks good on
the Hacker News front page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t that kind of blog post, though, and she makes a compelling argument
that almost earns the title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be &amp;ldquo;Why &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; Should Never Use MongoDB&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;m being pedantic,
but I think the emphasis makes the point clearer. The post is making an
assumption about you, and that assumption is this: you are not as smart as she
is and if you are not as smart as she is, how can you hope to avoid the problem
she is describing? I am not as smart as she is, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to learn from her
mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m an inexperienced software developer; a n00b. I haven&amp;rsquo;t watched a large
software system go from infancy to smouldering ruins, nor have I watched design
decisions explode in my face nine months after making them. And how could I
have? I&amp;rsquo;m an undergraduate student and there aren&amp;rsquo;t enough months of summer
jobs to string together to create those experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have many of these experiences of my own, I&amp;rsquo;m forced to use the
experiences of others. Let&amp;rsquo;s call these &lt;a href=&#34;http://aosabook.org/en/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;prosthetic experiences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Brave, humble, smart folks like Sarah Mei, who can talk about the projects
they&amp;rsquo;ve seen crash and burn, are a boon; prosthetic experiences can help me
think about design tradeoffs in ways I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise be able to without
dealing with those problems myself.  They help me develop paranoia in the right
places. Hopefully, it&amp;rsquo;ll help me avoid boring mistakes and make more
interesting messes instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not fun to write about your mistakes. But I like it when you do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>