<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tavish Armstrong</title>
    <link>http://example.org/tags/hack/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tavish Armstrong</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://example.org/tags/hack/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Architecture of Open Source Applications, Volume 2</title>
      <link>http://example.org/2012/05/08/the-architecture-of-open-source-applications-volume-2</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2012 22:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/2012/05/08/the-architecture-of-open-source-applications-volume-2</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The second volume of &lt;a href=&#34;http://aosabook.org/&#34;&gt;The Architecture of Open Source
Applications&lt;/a&gt; was just released thanks to the hard
work of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amyrbrown.ca/index.html&#34;&gt;Amy Brown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://third-bit.com/&#34;&gt;Greg
Wilson&lt;/a&gt;. I had the privilege of helping copyedit
a few chapters of the book. Here&amp;rsquo;s the blurb:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architects look at thousands of buildings during their training, and
study critiques of those buildings written by masters. In contrast,
most software developers only ever get to know a handful of large
programs well — usually programs they wrote themselves — and never
study the great programs of history. As a result, they repeat one
another’s mistakes rather than building on one another’s successes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second volume of The Architecture of Open Source Applications
aims to change that. In it, the authors of twenty-four open source
applications explain how their software is structured, and why. What
are each program&amp;rsquo;s major components? How do they interact? And what
did their builders learn during their development? In answering these
questions, the contributors to this book provide unique insights into
how they think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go buy it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lulu.com/shop/amy-brown-and-greg-wilson/the-architecture-of-open-source-applications-volume-ii/paperback/product-20111008.html&#34;&gt;at
Lulu&lt;/a&gt;
(ebook versions will also be available). It&amp;rsquo;ll be available on Amazon at
some point, but Lulu is preferred, because a greater percentage of the
price goes towards royalties — which are going to Amnesty International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strike&gt;A free online version will be up at some point next week.&lt;/strike&gt; The online
version is available
&lt;a href=&#34;http://aosabook.org&#34; title=&#34;The Architecture of Open Source Applications&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>